<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true historie of the late and lamentable aduentures of Don Sebastian king of Portugall after his imprisonment in Naples, vntill this present day, being now in Spaine at Saint Lucar de Barrameda.</title>
            <title>Histoire veritable des dernieres et piteuses adventures de Don Sebastian. English</title>
            <author>Teixeira, José, 1543-1604.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1602</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13573</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23865</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101268</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837084</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837084</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1392</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13573)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1392)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 978:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true historie of the late and lamentable aduentures of Don Sebastian king of Portugall after his imprisonment in Naples, vntill this present day, being now in Spaine at Saint Lucar de Barrameda.</title>
                  <title>Histoire veritable des dernieres et piteuses adventures de Don Sebastian. English</title>
                  <author>Teixeira, José, 1543-1604.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[14] leaves   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Simon Stafford and Iames Shaw,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1602.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By José Teixeira.</note>
                  <note>A translation of:  Histoire veritable des dernieres et piteuses adventures de Don Sebastian.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴[-A1] B-D⁴[-D4].</note>
                  <note>Imprint should read: "Printed by Simon Stafford for Iames Shaw"--STC.</note>
                  <note>Printer's device (McKerrow 281) on title page.</note>
                  <note>A1 and D4 probably blank, lacking.</note>
                  <note>Considerable print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sebastian, --  King of Portogual --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1392:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1392:1"/>
            <p>THE TRVE HISTORIE OF THE late and lamentable aduentures of <hi>Don Sebastian King of Portugall, after</hi> his impriſonment in Naples, vntill this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent day, being now in Spaine at <hi>Saint Lucar de Barrameda.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROMANS. 13.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>There is no power but from God.</p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <head>AVT NVNC AVT NVNQVAM</head>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Simon Stafford and James Shaw</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>AT LONDON</hi> Printed by Simon Stafford and Iames Shaw. 1602.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="history">
            <pb facs="tcp:1392:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1392:2"/>
            <head>THE TRVE HISTORIE of the late and lamentable aduentures <hi>of Don Sebastian King of Portugall,</hi> after his impriſonment in Naples, vntill <hi>this preſent day, being now in</hi> Spaine at Saint Lucar <hi>de Barrameda.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His vnfortunate King, <hi>Don Sebaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> hauing bene brought from <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> to <hi>Naples,</hi> was put in the caſtle of <hi>Oeuf,</hi> in a chamber, without any other furniture in it, then a halter &amp; a long knife of the length of halfe the arme: Where for the ſpace of three dayes, they neither gaue him ought to drinke or to eate, nor whereon to lie: Which ſpace, hee ſpent in continuall prayers, induring his croſſes with an incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible patience. On the fourth day after, the <hi>Auditor Generall,</hi> accompanied with two <hi>Notaries,</hi> came to viſite him, and found him, for his life, of good diſpoſition, &amp; maruailed exceedingly at him (for all of them did veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beleeue, that ſeeing himſelfe ſo ill intreated, he would
<pb facs="tcp:1392:3"/>in deſpaire haue hanged himſelfe, or with one of thoſe two inſtruments haue ended his dayes, which for that purpoſe were prepared and placed in that roome, or at leaſt incurre thereby ſome grieuous maladie) and ſaid vnto him, that if he would not deny, and ceaſe to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, what he had auouched and maintained, in repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting himſelfe to be <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> King of <hi>Portugall,</hi> hee ſhould neuer haue either drinke, meat, or lodging. To whom the king made anſwere:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doe what you will; for I ſhall neuer ſing any other ſong: and I beſeech God omnipotent, of his infinite goodnes and diuine mercy, that he will ſtretch out his powerfull hand, and aſſiſt me in theſe my troubles, and that hee will not ſuffer me to commit ſo foule a fault, or to fall into ſo great a miſchiefe, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to mine owne ſoule, that for feare and terrour of men, I ſhould come to denie the truth, and to confeſse a falſhood. God defend me from it. I am that ſelfe ſame</hi> Don Sebaſtian, <hi>king of</hi> Portugall, <hi>which in the yeare</hi> 1578. <hi>paſſed into</hi> Affricke <hi>againſt the Infidels, and the very ſame, who, to augment the name &amp; power of the Chriſtians, put my life in hazard: and am that vnfortunate Prince, who for the puniſhment of his ſinnes loſt a battaile, which loſſe begat ſo many miſaduentures, and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned ſo many changes in Chriſtendome. This is the verie truth, neyther can I ſay any other.</hi> With this anſwere, the <hi>Auditor</hi> &amp; his Notaries went their way. After this they began to giue him for his nouriſhment ſome bread and water: and ſome few dayes after, hee was allowed fiue crownes a moneth, and a man to wayte vpon him. The <hi>Viceroy</hi> of <hi>Naples</hi> laſt deceaſed, came to viſite him, and there paſſed betweene them that which hath bin publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by ſo many hands, &amp; ſet forth in ſo many langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Now, as ſoone as it was bruted abroad, and that
<pb facs="tcp:1392:3"/>fame had runne and told it through the world, that hee remained priſoner, &amp; that all men had leaue to ſee him, many perſons, of diuers, both qualities, and nations, made a voyage vnto <hi>Naples,</hi> onely to ſee him, and to ſpeake vnto him: And amongſt the reſt, many Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugals, ſome out of <hi>Portugal,</hi> and ſome from other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of their being, paſt into <hi>Italy,</hi> that they might with their owne proper eyes behold ſo admirable, and ſo rare a wonder. Many of the Portugals, eſpecially the elder ſort, who had ſeene him, and knew him; and ſome alſo of <hi>Caſtile,</hi> and other ſtrangers beſides, hauing ſeene him, and diſcourſed with him, confeſſed and maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that he was <hi>Don Sebaſtian,</hi> the true King of <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal.</hi> During the life of the ſaid Viceroy, his impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was not ſo auſtere nor ſo ſtrict as it was afterwards, when his ſonne ſucceeded in the ſaid gouernment, who kept him exceeding cloſe, and double garded, ſuffring him notwithſtanding to goe abroad on the Sundayes, and other feſtiuall dayes, for to heare maſſe in a Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel within the ſaid Caſtle. He liued in perpetual pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and faſtings. Euery Friday and Saturday, he faſted with bread and water. He did the like ſometimes alſo on other dayes, as on Mundayes, and Wedneſdayes. Hee often frequented the Sacraments, and vſed much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion; and all the Lent long fed nor ate of any thing ſaue only herbes and pulſe.</p>
            <p>The ſeuenteenth of <hi>Aprill</hi> laſt paſt, within a yeere after that he was deliuered to the Caſtilians, the ſaid Viceroy, who alſo is County of <hi>Lemos,</hi> ſonne to him that was deceaſed, married with the daughter of the Duke of <hi>Lerma,</hi> who now at this day is a gouernour in <hi>Spaine:</hi> At that time it was demaunded of him, that hee
<pb facs="tcp:1392:4"/>ſhould ſuddenly make anſwere, without any other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings or diligence in his cauſe, vnto that which on the fourth day was propoſed by the <hi>Auditor</hi> general, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied, as before we me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he replied.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That it was no lawful nor direct courſe, to take vpon them to examine and iudge him without proces: but rather that they ſhould preſent him to the Portugals, who had both nouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed him, knowne him, and ſerued him. For on their relation and their teſtimonie, ought to depend the true proofe and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of his buſineſſe: Affirming, that if it were poſſible for him to liue a thouſand yeeres longer, he would neuer anſwer otherwiſe: And that if they ſhould determine to doe iuſtice on him, without any other order or proofe, hee muſt take God for his only Iudge, who knowes the truth of this matter, and that he is the proper and true King of</hi> Portugall, Don Sebaſtian. <hi>Wherefore, if you are ſo diſpoſed, take your courſe in effecting that, vpon which heretofore you purpoſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The officers appointed for this affaire, being gone from him with this anſwere, he went incontinently and threw himſelfe downe on his knees before the Crucifix, and began to diſpoſe and prepare himſelfe for death. He faſted the ſpace of three dayes with bread &amp; water: He made his generall confeſsion, and receiued the holy Sacraments. As he thus attended his lateſt houre, before the ſaid month of <hi>Aprill</hi> was ended, they ſent againe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him for his finall anſwere. To which meſſage hee made the like anſwere as before. And vpon theſe his laſt words, hee was iudged and condemned by the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtilians, to be led in ignominy through the ſtreets of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> and from thence to labour in the Gallies all the reſt of his life.</p>
            <p>The laſt day of the ſaid moneth, they brought him
<pb facs="tcp:1392:4"/>out of the Caſtle, and mounted him on an Aſſe, &amp; led him openly thorow the ſtreetes of the City, three Trumpets marching afore him, with a Cryer, who cryed with a lowd voyce, <hi>This is the iuſtice which his Catholike Maieſtie hath commaunded to bee executed. Hee hath commaunded this man ſhould be thus ſhamefully led vp and downe, and that be ſhould perpetually be doom'd to the Galleys, for naming himſelfe to be</hi> Don Sebaſtian <hi>King of Portugall, being no other then a Calabrian.</hi> And ſtill before the Cryer beganne, the Trumpets ſounded, and ſo continued to the end. And when they named <hi>King,</hi> he would cry alowd, <hi>Why, ſo I am.</hi> And when they ſayd, <hi>Being no other then a Calabrian:</hi> hee would anſwere, <hi>That is falſe.</hi> Yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in the repetition of theſe wordes, all the while that they were pronounced by the Cryer, hee no whit hindred the courſe of iuſtice, nor once moued himſelfe againſt it.</p>
            <p>Now muſt you note, that the Caſtilians not kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing how to verifie that he was the ſaid <hi>Marcus Tul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Cartizzone,</hi> as they indowed him withall at the firſt, when he was deliuered vnto them, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claymed him at that howre, by the indefinite name of a <hi>Calabrian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This act bringeth an extreme amazement to al the whole city, and ingenders a great ſorrow, &amp; cauſeth much compunction in the hearts of all men; inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much, that they went away ſtroken with wonder, and full of aſtoniſhment. They looked one vpon another with a ſilent ſtrangeneſſe, and were vnable to vtter ſo much as one word one to another, the
<pb facs="tcp:1392:5"/>greatneſſe of their griefe ſtopping the paſſage of their ſpeach. And if any amongſt them were heretofore perſwaded, that he was a <hi>Calabrian,</hi> after they had now beheld his owne proper perſon, &amp; this ſo ſtrange a ſpectacle, they were confirmed in this beleefe, and did certainely aſſure themſelues, that he whom they thus reprochefully led vp and downe vpon an Aſſe, was the very right &amp; true <hi>Don Sebaſtian,</hi> King of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugall;</hi> and they were touched with ſuch great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſsion and remorſefull fellow-feeling, in beholding this his miſerable eſtate; and the iniuſtice wherewith they did intreate him, that they were not able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraine from teares: the ſighes and lamentations of one, inciting the reſt to the ſame, who mourned and bewayled his miſerie, whileſt the King himſelfe cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out in this pitifull maner:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I am in the hands of mine enemies, who worke what themſelues will vpon this my body, but my ſoule I recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend vnto God, who hath created it, and knowes the truth, and can witnes for me, that I am the ſame, whom I profeſſe and ſay I am.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After they had carried him thus throughout the Citie, they brought him to the Kings royall Gallies, whereinto he was no ſooner entred, but they preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pulled off his owne apparrell, and put vpon him a flauiſh attire, and placed him at the prow of the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, where hee remained a whole day: and the next day following, they put him with a gard, in a little Barke that was linked to the Galley, whither there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired a great concourſe of people of diuers nations: Amongſt the which, were preſent, a great number of
<pb facs="tcp:1392:5"/>noble perſonages, and of very honourable houſes, who ſteadily viewing his viſage, and marking him with an eſpeciall attention, and a moſt ſearching eye, <hi>Without doubt</hi> (ſaid they) <hi>this is that true</hi> D. Sebaſtian, <hi>King of</hi> Portugall.</p>
            <p>The ſift day, they rankt him in the Galleyes, and ſhaued off the haires both of his head and beard, the which were gathered vp, &amp; kept by thoſe that ſtood by, as a moſt precious thing, and of great eſteeme.</p>
            <p>This being done, they fettred him with chaynes, ſignifying vnto him, that he ſhould not be bound to rowe. Some French Lords were preſent at moſt of theſe proceedings: and amongſt the reſt, a ſonne of <hi>Monſieur de Berault</hi> (who is now at this day nomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for to be Ambaſſadour of Caſtile) and a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, who is a follower of his, with ſome others of the ſame ſute.</p>
            <p>In theſe dayes of ſo great affliction, the King ceaſed not to continue in his dayly prayers and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtings, with ſuch admiration of thoſe that beheld it, that they held him for a Saint: and by the meanes of his patience, modeſtie, and other apparant de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of his vertues, he gained ſo much repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation amongſt thoſe with whom he liued, that they were inforced to confeſſe, that the truth of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was couered and hidden, by the inuentions and ſubtilties of his enemies, and maintained, that he was the rightfull <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> King of <hi>Portugall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many of verie good qualities haue writ out of <hi>Naples</hi> into diuers partes of <hi>Europe,</hi> touching the ſucceſſe of this affayre, according to the trueth
<pb facs="tcp:1392:6"/>thereof, and in ſuch forcible maner, that as many as are either in the Court of Rome, or in Italy, are perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to beleeue, &amp; doe hold moſt conſtantly for true, that this miſerable Prince, is the ſame perſon hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth himſelfe to be.</p>
            <p>But ſome will happely ſay, that he doth deſerue farre more grieuous chaſtiſement, becauſe hee eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping aliue from the battell of Affricke, ſo much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſed in the world, and comming afterwards vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne into his owne kingdome of Portugall, hee did not demaund it againe, leauing it as a prey to his enemies; which hath occaſioned ſo many mens deathes, ſo many and ſo diuers miſaduentures, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny miſchiefes, afflictions, and miſeries, as haue hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thereby, and haue croſſed thoſe Chriſtian peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple theſe 22. yeeres: as one, who ſhould haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferd the publike good, before his owne particular imaginations, and priuate fantaſies. But whoſoeuer ſhall take knowledge of his pure vertue, pietie, feare of God, wiſdome, and vnderſtanding, will ſing ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſong, and onely ſay this: <hi>Sic erat in fatis:</hi> and that God would haue it ſo, to the intent, that in the law of grace, there ſhould be found another <hi>Iob,</hi> like vnto him in the law of nature.</p>
            <p>Theſe Galleyes paſſed from <hi>Naples</hi> into <hi>Spayne,</hi> where ſome do report, that they ſaw him at <hi>Barcelon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne,</hi> in one of the Kings royall Galleyes, and that hee ſat on the third ſeat, and that they vſed him very wel, and ſerued him with verie much honour, and with great reſpects.</p>
            <p>We beleeue well the former, but not the latter, as
<pb facs="tcp:1392:6"/>it ſhall appeare by that we ſhal manifeſt hereafter: for they are but tales and fables, divulged by his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, who haue publiſht it ſo abroad, for to cloake their malicious wickedneſſe, and their treaſonable intents, and to conſerue the good loue and fauour of ſuch as loue him with all their hearts, and who with all the arte they can, with all their ſoule, and with all their power ſeeke to regaine him, &amp; to acknowledge him for their Lord and Maſter: whereas the other, preferring their owne particular intereſt, and forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting wholy the common good, haue quite loſt both the remembrance of their loyaltie, and the Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wherein they ſtand bound to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Bercelonne,</hi> the Gallies entred into the Ocean ſea, where they remayned till the beginning of the month of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> at the port of <hi>Saint Lucar de Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rameda.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Currier from his Catholike Maieſtie recounted to the thrice Chriſtian King, the cauſe why the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd veſſels paſt forth of the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> ſea into the <hi>Ocean,</hi> which was a rebellion in <hi>Angra,</hi> a City in the Ile of <hi>Tergere,</hi> which is the chiefeſt of the Iles, which they call by the name of <hi>Aſſores,</hi> which is the key of all the Ocean ſea: for thoſe that come out of Affricke, out of Aſia and America, are conſtrayned to paſſe that way, as to the principal But of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uigation. The Ile is ſituated in 39. degrees, and ſome minutes, betweene the <hi>Septentrion,</hi> and the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The certainty of this inſurrection, is not yet to
<pb facs="tcp:1392:7"/>this day made fully knowne. Some ſay, that the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugals</hi> did riſe againſt the Catholike King, a Noble man of Spayne being a party with them. Others, that the Gouernour of the Ile, being by nation a <hi>Caſtilian,</hi> did mightily baſtenado a Captaine of his regiment; who weighing with himſelf, that he could not challenge his ſuperior the field, &amp; that he remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in an Ile inuironed round about with the ſea, &amp; 300. leagues from <hi>Lisborne,</hi> he reſolued to take ſome other courſe to ſatisfie his vengeance vpon him. For effecting of which reuenge, he diſcouered his inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to his ſouldiours, and eſpecially to the <hi>Portugals</hi> of the ſaid Ile: whome hee finding propitious, and fully bent to yeeld him their beſt aſsiſtance, for to make himſelfe ſatiſfaction for the wrong he was of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred, hee determined to kill the Gouernour, and to riſe with the whole Ile, in fauour of the <hi>Portugals:</hi> which was effected after the ſame maner, as it was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued on.</p>
            <p>This reuolt was the cauſe that his Catholike Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie cauſed his Galleyes to come from <hi>Naples</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Ocean.</p>
            <p>Yet for all this, will I not deliuer neither the one nor the other cauſe for curra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: for they are but fables, framed out of the forge of the enemy, whoſe cuſtome it is to ſow ſuch falſe tales, to ſee how the world will ſtand affected with it, and to diſcouer the heartes, as well of the nobler, as the vulgar ſort. It is rather to be thought, that his Maieſtie commaunded the ſayd Galleyes to come out of <hi>Naples</hi> into the Ocean, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the rumour of thoſe forces that were rayſed in
<pb facs="tcp:1392:7"/>England, being deſigned (as ſome ſay) to enter <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whatſoeuer they ſay, ſo it was, that his Galleyes came downe thither: and it ſhall ſuffice vs for our purpoſe, to knowe for certayne, that the Royall Galley of <hi>Naples,</hi> in which <hi>Don Sebaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> King of <hi>Portugall</hi> was put, rides at <hi>Saint Lucar de Barrameda,</hi> and that the ſaid <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> is within her in the maner aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>On the twelfth or thirteenth day of the ſaid mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, there arriued in Fraunce in a Shippe of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chelers,</hi> two French marchants, well knowne to bee men of credit and of trueth, who did aſſure, as well by word of mouth, as by letters written to perſons of Honour in <hi>Paris,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That they haue ſeene the foreſayd priſoner at <hi>Saint Lucar de Barrameda,</hi> within the Royall Galley of <hi>Naples:</hi> And that they ſpake vnto him: And that they ſawe him in chaynes poore and miſerable: And that they offered him Lynnen, and Siluer, and other commodities, which hee would by no meanes take, but refuſed their kindneſſe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned them thankes: And that hee brooked his affliction with wonderfull patience: And that all they of the Galleyes did acknowledge him to bee the ſame that himſelfe had ſayd he was, and did ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally call him King: And that he is ſerued by two Galley-ſlaues that are Turkes: That hee labours not at the Oare; But in all things elſe is vſed like the reſt of the ſlaues: And that the Duke of <hi>Medina Sidonia</hi> and his wife, had a deſire to ſee him; who hauing
<pb facs="tcp:1392:8"/>talked a long time with him, the King demaunded of him, if hee had that ſword ſtill which hee gaue him, when he embarked himſelfe for Barbarie.</p>
            <p>The Duke made anſwere, that indeed <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> King of <hi>Portugall</hi> preſented him with a ſword, which he beſtowed vpon him before his imbarking, which he had cauſed to be kept in his Armory amongſt the reſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Since that you haue it then</hi> (replied the King) <hi>I pray you let mee intreate that it may bee brought hither: for although it be now foure and twenty yeres ſince I gaue it you, I doubt not but I ſhall know it full well.</hi> The Duke had commanded ſome douzen to be brought: the which the King hauing ſeuerally viewed, told him, <hi>Mine is not amongſt any of theſe.</hi> Then the Duke willed they ſhould bring all the reſt. And the King eſpying it in the hands of him that brought them, <hi>Loe, Duke</hi> (ſayd he) <hi>behold the ſword which I gaue you, when I paſt into Affricke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There was in the company of the Ducheſſe, a <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gro,</hi> whom the King knew, &amp; ſaid, that he had ſerued him for the waſhing of his lynnen, being one of his Launderers, when hee raigned in <hi>Portugall.</hi> The Duke ſeeing theſe things to bee ſo apparant, and ſo probably true, that they ſeemed miraculous vnto him, bleſt himſelfe with many a croſſe, and was ſeene to goe from him with a heauy and a ſorrowfull coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and weeping, as it were, through compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and meere pitty, to ſee ſo miſerable a Prince, in ſo wretched and vnhappy an eſtate. And the moſt part of the <hi>Caſtilians</hi> themſelues, ſubiects to King
<pb facs="tcp:1392:8"/>
               <hi>Philip,</hi> amazed with theſe ſo many ſignes and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of trueth, (howbeit they dare not ſpeake it openly, yet notwithſtanding in their priuate diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) they wil not ſtick to ſay, That it is impoſsible, that this man ſhould be any other, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the true <hi>Don Sebaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an;</hi> And that it is to be feared, that God will ſwallow them all in hell, if the Catholike King reſtore not all that vnto him, which of right appertayneth vnto him. But thoſe, who doe not looke on theſe great miracles, with the eyes of pitty, ſay that he is poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with a deuill.</p>
            <p>This Duke (if I am not deceyued) was called <hi>D. Alphonſe de Guzman le Bon,</hi> the tenth County of <hi>Niebla,</hi> and the ſeuenth Duke of <hi>Medina Sidonia,</hi> who in the yeere 1578. the King <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> arriuing at <hi>Cales,</hi> for to goe into <hi>Affricke,</hi> receyued him with great royaltie, magnificent feaſtings, vvith Tilting, &amp; Tourning, vvith Bul-bayting, and other ſportes and paſtimes, ſuch as the Ile could afford.</p>
            <p>The ſayd King continued eight dayes with the Duke, who (they ſay) tooke much trauaile with him, to diſſwade him from paſſing into <hi>Barbary</hi> in his owne perſon.</p>
            <p>This conſidered, men need not to think it ſtrange if the Duke had a deſire to ſee him, and alſo to ſpeake with him: Nor that likewiſe which the Rochelers report, touching the ſword, and the <hi>Negro,</hi> ſince that the wife and Ladie of the ſayd Duke, is <hi>Dame Anne de Silua,</hi> daughter to <hi>K. Gomes de Silua,</hi> a <hi>Portugall,</hi> and Prince of <hi>Eboli,</hi> who gouerned the kingdome of <hi>Caſtile</hi> for many yeres, who might verie well retaine
<pb facs="tcp:1392:9"/>the ſayd <hi>Negro</hi> in her ſervice, by reaſon he had beene brought vp in the Princes houſe of <hi>Portugail.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee haue diuers letters written from <hi>Cales,</hi> into many places round about, which wee finde to be as followeth:</p>
            <p>There arriued out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> ſixe or ſeuen Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants, Inhabitants of this towne, men of the moſt credit &amp; wealth amongſt them, who reported they had ſeene <hi>Don Sebaſtian,</hi> King of <hi>Portugall,</hi> in the Kings Galley of <hi>Naples,</hi> at <hi>Saint Lucar de Barrameda;</hi> and that they ſaw him chayned as a priſoner, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated as the reſt of the ſlaues, but ſerued with more reſpect, and free from the oare: which fauour, it is thought, was obtayned for him by the Popes fauour.</p>
            <p>They added moreouer, that many old men, <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gals</hi> of diuers ſorts, in great abundance, came thither to ſee him, and that all of them did confeſſe and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne, that this was the true <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> King of <hi>Portugall;</hi> and that the <hi>Caſtilians</hi> cryed with alowd voyce, in theſe termes, which we haue here aboue mentioned, touching the wrath of God hanging o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer Spayne.</p>
            <p>And if wee ſhall but weigh all the ſucceſſes of this King, his peregrinations thorow the world, his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments, his deliuerance out of <hi>Venice,</hi> the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of his comming from <hi>Florence</hi> vnto <hi>Naples,</hi> his ſentence, and execution vpon it, it makes the caſe appeare in our ſight, miraculous and full of wonder: But aboue all, his imbarking and arriuall at Saint <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>car de Barrameda.</hi> And yet beſide all theſe, this is a rare and extraordinary thing, that the Gallies, comming
<pb facs="tcp:1392:9"/>downe from <hi>Naples</hi> into the Ocean ſea, did ſute in ſuch conformity, and correſpondencie with the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent old prophecies, which touch theſe aduentures.</p>
            <p>The reuer end father, <hi>Dvctor Eampayo,</hi> a religious &amp; holy man, of the order of Preachers, being at <hi>Paris</hi> the laſt yeere, hath aſſured many men, that hee had ſeene in the Library of S. <hi>Victor,</hi> in a certayne booke, a prophecy, which we wil openly deliuer vnto you: to wit, <hi>That the King,</hi> Don Sebaſtian, <hi>ſhould come out of Naples, vpon a horſe of wood, which out of the Mediter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranean ſea, ſhould enter into the Ocean, and that his horſe ſhould reſt at</hi> Saint Lucar de Barrameda.</p>
            <p>See, what father <hi>Sampayo</hi> hath trucly recounted to theſe perſons touching this Prophecie: the ſame is confeſſed and confirmed anew, by the religious men of that Monaſtery: For it hath bene communicated and declared to diuers of them. Alſo, they haue writ the verie ſame, to ſome of his friends. And within the ſelfe ſame Library they haue ſhewed the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to ſome ſuch ſecular Gentlemen, as ſtand well af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to the liberty of this vnfortunate King. And for as much as the ſaid father <hi>Sampayo</hi> is far fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence, we cannot cite the very words of the prophecy, nor the Author of it. Yet notwithſtanding, it ſhall make very well for that we haue in hand, if wee ſhall but know that which is found written touching the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe, &amp; proſperous haps of this vnhappy Prince, by men of great learning, &amp; holines of life: which if we do, we may the more eaſily be excuſed. Saint <hi>Iſioore,</hi> a very wiſe and learned man, and of the bloud royall, as being the ſonne of <hi>Thtodora,</hi> and of <hi>Seuerian,</hi> ſonne to <hi>Thierry,</hi> King of the <hi>Oſtrogothes</hi> and of <hi>Italy,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1392:10"/>who flouriſhed about the yeere 580. hath left vnto vs in writing: <hi>Occultus Rex, bis piè datus, in Hiſpaniam veniet in equo ligneo, quem multi videntes, illum eſſe non credent, &amp;c.</hi> Which is as much to ſay, A ſecret and vnknowne King, exceeding deuoutly giuen, ſhall come into Spayne vpon a woodden horſe, which many men ſeeing, ſhall not beleeue it is he, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>This here, is found to be publiſhed in a ſtrange ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture lately imprinted:</p>
            <p>A Shooe-maker of Portugall, named <hi>Bandarra,</hi> borne in the towne of <hi>Trancoſo,</hi> who liued heere a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſome 300. yeeres ſince, hath left vnto vs in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in Portugall verſe, very many Prophecies vpon diuers and ſundry ſubiects: Amongſt the which, there are found ſome, which intreat <hi>Del Incubierto: vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delicet,</hi> Of the concealed and hidden Prince; in one part whereof, we haue obſerued the accompliſhment in the perſon of King <hi>Don Sebaſtian.</hi> And if thoſe which remaine behinde, ſhall proue but ſo true as thoſe that are paſt, doubtleſſe wee ſhall ſee this King ſeated in his Royall throne.</p>
            <p>The poore labouring people of Portugall retaine this as an old tradition:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That a time ſhall come, wherein a King, whoſe name ſhall be as it were</hi> De Beſtia, <hi>ſhall diſappeare for a time; and that after that hee and his Realme ſhall haue ſuffred many afflictions and calamities, the verie ſelfe ſame King, whom all the world holdeth for dead, ſhall riſe againe, and gayne his throne with incredible happineſſe.</hi> In which tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we are to note one thing, concerning the name of <hi>Beſtia:</hi> For the Peſants of Portugall, in ſtead of
<pb facs="tcp:1392:10"/>ſaying, <hi>Sebaſtian,</hi> pronounce <hi>Beſtiam:</hi> ſo that, taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the laſt letter of the word, there remaines <hi>Bestia.</hi> Moreouer, we may alſo perſwade ourſelues, that this tradition of thoſe baſe, ruſticke, and barbarous men, ſhall haue his full accompliſhment in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this Prince, hitherto ſo vnfortunate. It is no ſuch ſtrange &amp; vnvſuall thing, to ſee God permit, that we behold his ſecrets in the mouth of ignorant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, ſince that his Sonne hath taught vs, <hi>Abſcondiſti ea a ſapientibus, &amp; reuelaſti ea parvulis.</hi> And we may as well, by the permiſsion of God, ſee this ruſticke pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie fulfilled, as they did that, which runneth tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the mouthes of the laborers of <hi>Beaulſe,</hi> in theſe latter yeeres of the King that was, which was by tradition deliuered ſtill from the father to the ſonne.</p>
            <q>
               <l>The yeere one thouſand, fiue hundred, eightie nine,</l>
               <l>Anew King vnto the throne of Portugall ſhall clime.</l>
               <l>The yeere one thouſand, fiue hundred and ninety,</l>
               <l>Farre more hares, then ſheepe ſhall you ſee.</l>
            </q>
            <p>We haue alſo elſewhere, an other old fellow, who hath compoſed a booke in Caſtilian verſe, which ſerues as an explication of thoſe prophecies of Saint <hi>Iſidore,</hi> and of ſome other, who haue writ of the <hi>Incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bierto.</hi> In which booke I haue read ſome 45. yeres ſince, many curious things, which if I could remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber them, would at this time ſtand me in good ſtead. But becauſe I read them in my youth, without any notice of things to come, or imagining of any chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges or reuolutions to happen in the world theſe 24.
<pb facs="tcp:1392:11"/>yeeres paſt: and beſides, being then vncapable of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding them, made me the more negligent in the apprehenſion of them: onely my memory hath in a confuſed maner, furniſhed me with a Poeme of ſeuen lines, very fit for our preſent purpoſe. And not long ſince, a Gentleman of <hi>Portugall,</hi> a faithfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant to his King, and very deſirous of his countries liberty, gaue it me in writing.</p>
            <l>
               <hi>Vendra &amp; Incubierto,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Vendra cierto.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Entrera en el huerto,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Por el puerto.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Qu'eſta mas a ca del muro.</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Y lo que pareſce eſcuro,</hi>
            </l>
            <l>
               <hi>Se vra claro, yabierto.</hi>
            </l>
            <p>Which is as much to ſay:</p>
            <l>The vnknowne ſhall come:</l>
            <l>He ſhall come for certaine, and ſhall enter at the garden,</l>
            <l>By the gate, which is neereſt to the wall.</l>
            <l>And that which ſeemeth darke and obſeure,</l>
            <l>Shall appeare full cleare, and be diſcouered.</l>
            <p>For the better vnderſtanding of theſe verſes, wee are to vnderſtand what this garden, and what this wall is: for the expoſition and vnderſtanding of theſe two words, ſhall giue vs light to the reſt, and ſhall lay open to our view, thoſe admirable things, which a ſimple Poeme prophecieth vnto vs.</p>
            <p>We are then to vnderſtand, that this garden may
<pb facs="tcp:1392:11"/>bee taken for the countrey, which extends it ſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Mount <hi>Calpe,</hi> which is in <hi>Spaine,</hi> at the mouth of the Streight of <hi>Gibraltar,</hi> fronting on Mount <hi>Abyla,</hi> which is ſituated on the other ſide of the ſayd Streight, in <hi>Affricke,</hi> which are the two Mountaynes, which are named by the Ancient, <hi>Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cules Pillers,</hi> as farre as the riuer, which the <hi>Latines</hi> call <hi>Baetis,</hi> and is named now at this day, by the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants, <hi>Guadal quiber,</hi> a name, impoſed by the <hi>Moores,</hi> after they had made themſelues Lords of <hi>Spaine,</hi> which ſigniſieth in our language, Great-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: for <hi>Guad,</hi> in the <hi>Arabian</hi> tongue, is as much as water, and <hi>Quiber</hi> ſignifieth great.</p>
            <p>The Ile of <hi>Cales</hi> is in that countrey, and was once farre greater, then now it is. All this countrey is very ſertill, plentifull, and delightſome.</p>
            <p>Ancient Authors doe report of it, that if their ſheepe ſhould goe but thirty dayes without letting of bloud, they would die with fatneſſe.</p>
            <p>In this countrey did <hi>Homer</hi> dwell before he grew blind, which was in the yeere 1;07. after the flood, and 255. before the foundation of <hi>Rome,</hi> and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand before the incarnatiou of Chriſt. In thoſe daies they called it <hi>Meleſegines.</hi> They that haue ſeene the fruitfulneſſe and good temperature thereof, affirme, that theſe were the Eliſian fieldes, whither the gods ſent the ſoules of the bleſſed. Whence we ſee cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that this countrey is the garden of <hi>Spatne,</hi> and ſo we likewiſe call it.</p>
            <p>Yet there are ſome Authors, notwithſtanding, who maintaine &amp; approue with very ſtrong and euident
<pb facs="tcp:1392:12"/>reaſons, that Lisborne is the garden of Spaine, with the appurtenances thereunto belonging: For as much as it is a very pleaſant Territorie, large, fertill, plentifull, fayre, and delectable, wherein grow great abundance of all fruits, the moſt excellent, and the moſt perfit that <hi>Europe</hi> affordeth.</p>
            <p>Your elder writers affirme, that the mares that liue thereabout, will be impregned by the wind, and that the coltes which come of them, ſeeme rather to flye then runne, ſo ſwift they are of foot.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vliſſes</hi> (whom writers allot vnto vs, as ſounder of the ſayd Citie) and his companions, arriued after his ſhipwracke, in theſe quarters, and entring into the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean ſea by Tagus, moued by the fertilneſſe of the Territorie, with the waters, &amp; the abundance of fiſh, that were bred in the ſayd riuer, being ſo deepe, and ſo marueilous fit for all kind of commodities, beſides the great ſtore of Gold, which ſeemed to be in thoſe ſands, he named it <hi>Theodora,</hi> which in the Greeke tongue, ſignifieth Gods gift. So that the garden of Spaine is that countrey, which we affirme to bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the mount <hi>Calpe,</hi> and the riuer of <hi>Guadiana:</hi> Or elſe the towne of Lisborne, with her Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories.</p>
            <p>The King <hi>Don Sebaſtian</hi> hauing entred ſome of theſe parts with proſperity, it importeth vs a little for the verification of this Prophecie, whether the one or the other be the garden of Spaine.</p>
            <p>Touching the wall, all they that are well ſeene and practiſed in the ancient Hiſtories of Spayne, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that it is the Ile of <hi>Cales,</hi> which they call <hi>Gades,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1392:12"/>and by reaſon of the affinity of the G. with the C. is conuerted into the name of <hi>Cades.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the better declaring from whence this name came, it is neceſſarie that wee heere alleage ſome ancient Hiſtories, who teach vs, that there are ſixe men that beare the name of <hi>Hercules:</hi> whereof, two of them haue ſtifled eche others reputation. One was ſonne vnto <hi>Iupiter</hi> &amp; <hi>Alcmena:</hi> the other, ſonne of the ſame father, and of <hi>Aſteria</hi> ſiſter to <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tona.</hi> And this <hi>Hercules</hi> is adored with great reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce at <hi>Tyr.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Hiſtories doe report, that hee commaunded the <hi>Gaditanes</hi> by a dreame, who were the Inhabitants of that Citie, that they ſhould paſſe into Spayne, and build a Temple vnto him in <hi>Cales,</hi> where his name ſhould be held in veneration.</p>
            <p>For to accompliſh this commaundement, the <hi>Gaditanes</hi> imbarked themſelues in the yeere two hundred thirty fiue, after the foundation of Rome; and ſayling by the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> ſea, they entred the Ocean: and not farre from the mouth of the Streight, they landed at <hi>Cales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There beganne they to build a towne, obſeruing the cuſtomes and Ceremonies of the Hetruſcians, who did (as <hi>M. Varro</hi> mentioneth) couple a Bull and a Cowe vnder one yoke, and ſo made a deepe furrowe with their plovv-ſhare, in a circular or round figure, whoſe circuit they drew as large as the City ſhould bee, which they intended to build. The plowe ſhare made the furrow, and the earth they threw vp, formed their vvalles. So did <hi>Romulus,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1392:13"/>when he vndertooke the foundation of Rome: as it is ſtoried by <hi>Dioniſius Halicarneſſeus.</hi> So did <hi>Aeneas</hi> alſo, according to the teſtimony of <hi>Virgil.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Interea Aeneas orbem deſignat aratro.</q>
            <p>And thus in this maner, was the ſayd place held afterwards for a thing holy, and religious.</p>
            <p>As ſoone as the building of this towne and temple was bruted in the world, great multitudes out of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, Affricke,</hi> and <hi>Aſia,</hi> came to ſee it. And in after yeeres, the <hi>Garthaginians,</hi> conſidering that the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants thereof, as being all of one countrie, (for they and the <hi>Gaditanes</hi> came both out of <hi>Tyr</hi>) would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue ſtill friends vnto them, determined to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take the conqueſt of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the better effecting their deſigne, they cloaked their ambition, with pietie and religion, as I ſhall ſhew you: giuing the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to vnderſtand, that it was not fit, ſince ſo many out of all parts of the world came to viſit this Citie, and the temple belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vnto it, and to doe ſacrifice vnto the God there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, of whom they had receiued ſuch exceeding bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits, that the ſaid God ſhould bee worſhipped in ſo poore a temple, and of ſo baſe a ſtructure, the walles thereof being no better then durt and earth: And therefore would intreat them, that they might haue leaue to build a greater, a richer, and more ſumptuous temple.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Spaniards,</hi> not ſuſpecting any ill that might ſucceed, nor any way being ielous of the <hi>Carthagini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:1392:13"/>at that time, did eaſily condeſcend to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, ſuffering them to obtaine whatſoeuer they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired.</p>
            <p>Preſently hereupon, the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> began, with incredible haſte to build a mightie huge temple of ſquared ſtone, and ſo ſtrong, that it might ſerue them in ſtead of a caſtle, for the effecting of this their inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>There were alſo all along the temple ſome ſtrong buildings, ſaying they were to ſcrue for the Prieſts, the officers, and the ſeruants of the ſayd temple.</p>
            <p>Not content with this, acquainting the <hi>Spaniards</hi> with the bad entertainment, which thoſe receiued which came with ſuch great deuotion, and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tooke ſuch long iournies for to viſite the houſe of this their God, that they might haue where to retire themſelues, and to ſhelter themſelues for all ſeaſons, that they would permit them to build a greater nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of houſes, for to lodge and receiue theſe poore pilgrimes.</p>
            <p>In a word, the <hi>Carthaginians</hi> obtayned all that they would: and ioyning one houſe to another, they made a very ſtrong place, by meanes whereof, they grew great Lords in <hi>Spaine.</hi> And the ſame report is now at this day very common alſo in the mouthes of many. When the Earle of <hi>Eſſex</hi> tooke the ſaid towne by force, the Inhabitants trembled, and cried out, Is it poſsible that the walles of <hi>Spayne</hi> ſhould bee taken by the enemie? O God, what ſhall we doe?</p>
            <p>Out of this, which hath bin ſaid, you may clearely ſee, that this is that wall, and that garden, which the
<pb facs="tcp:1392:14"/>Author of theſe Prophecies hath ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of in his ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. So that in knowing this, wee may eaſily haue knowledge of the gate which is on the hither ſide of the wall, which muſt be that of <hi>Saint Lucar de Barra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meda,</hi> which is on the other ſide in the Ocean ſea, ſome fiue leagues diſtant from <hi>Cales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God graunt that this vertuous and holy Prince, <hi>Don Sebaſtian,</hi> King of <hi>Portugall,</hi> fulfilling all that which is prophecied of him, may enter into the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſsion of his kingdome, for the peace and tranquilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his countries, &amp; the common good of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome. <hi>Amen.</hi> Farewell, the laſt of Auguſt. 1602.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <p>AFter I had ended this preſent diſcourſe, newes came out of diuers places, and letters ſent by many perſons worthy of credit, who confirme all this that hath beene ſpoken of <hi>D. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſtian:</hi> Adding withall that the Duke of <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina Sidonia</hi> ſent afterward aboord the Gallies, foure men, which had both ſeene, knowne, ſpoken, and ſerued the ſaid King all the time hee lay at <hi>Cales,</hi> before hee paſt into <hi>Affrike,</hi> which were eight dayes, for to ſee, and examine, whether hee were the verie ſame or no. Theſe men ſaw him, ſpake to him, and demaunded him many things, himſelfe not knowing to what end they thus exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined him: VVhorenurning to the Duke, did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouch with many othes, That this man, was that
<pb facs="tcp:1392:14"/>verie ſelfe ſame right and true <hi>Don Sebaſtian,</hi> King of <hi>Portugall,</hi> whome bee had receiued at <hi>Cales,</hi> with ſuch great ioy and feaſting, in the yere <hi>1578.</hi> Some ſay that the <hi>Duke</hi> writ letters of all this that had paſſed vnto the Catholike King: And beſides, that with theſe his letters, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of what he had ſeene, and heard, he ſent the ſaid men for to teſtifie the tru<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th of it.</p>
            <p>God grant for his mercies ſake, and for our deliuerie out ſo many troubles and miſeries, that thoſe Prophecies ſet downe in the two laſt lines of thoſe verſes in the Caſtilian tongue, before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited, may quickly be fulfilled, to wit:</p>
            <q>
               <l>Y lo, que pareſce eſcuro</l>
               <l>Se vra claro, y abierto.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>GEntle Reader, there are many more proofes and teſtimonies of this miſerable King, which ſhall ere long be publiſhed, with a declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of all his time imployed, ſince the battell in</hi> Affrike, <hi>1578. till the month of</hi> Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember <hi>laſt paſt. 1602.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
